Finding Aid for University of Michigan Hillel records, 1935-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Hillel records 1935-2008
University of Michigan Hillel.
1.5 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
2009059 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Hillel records cover the student organization's contribution to Jewish campus life. The collection consists primarily of calendar of events, newsletters, some correspondence, newspaper clippings, board minutes, brochures, programs, and posters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated January, 2009 by the University of Michigan Hillel (donor number 1346 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research. No use or copying of donor lists for personal or professional gain.
In 1926, the University of Michigan Hillel became the 3rd Hillel Foundation established in North America. The student organization originally went under the name B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation. Before moving into a house at 1429 Hill Street, Hillel was situated in two different locations at the University. However, by 1951, the house on Hill Street became too small to house the growing organization and was replaced by a larger building. This larger building was then replaced in 1988 with the present Mandell Berman Center.
Over the decades, Hillel has grown to become the second largest student organization at the University of Michigan. Along with serving the religious needs of the campus Jewish community with kosher meal programs, religious education and holiday services, Hillel has enriched the larger University community through its many political, social and cultural events. Some Hillel sponsored events include the Hill Street Forum, Hill Street Cinema, Conference on the Holocaust, and Israel Conference Day.
The records of the University of Michigan Hillel cover the period between 1935 and 2008. The collection consists primarily of calendar of events, newsletters, some correspondence, newspaper clippings, board minutes, brochures, programs, and posters. The collection contains the following series: Administrative/Background, Scrapbooks, Press/Publications, and Events.
Subjects:
Jewish students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Jews--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Religion.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan Hillel.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Construction--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hill Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan Hillel.; Zwerdling, Osias.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Posters.; Scrapbooks.
- Administrative/Background
  Administrative/Background series documents the student organization's history, organizational structure, and early financial activities. The series contains an annotated chronology, brochures, board minutes, lease agreement, warranty deed, and some correspondence. The series also includes photographs and material related to the 1951 construction of the University of Michigan Hillel Building on 1429 Hill Street.
  - Hillel Organizational Notebook, 1942-1960 (Box 1)
  - History/Background Material, 1940-1988 (Box 1)
  - Legal and Financial Documents, 1942-1988 (Box 1)
    (contains lease agreement, warranty deed, and trust agreement)
  - 1429 Hill Street Building, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Board Meetings and Minutes, 1942, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Fundraiser Mailings, 2001 undated (Box 1)
  - Scholarship Funds, 1945-1974 (Box 1)
    (Photograph of chairperson and scholarship fund founder Osias Zwerdling)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks series contains scrapbooks created during the mid 1930s and the early 1940s. The scrapbooks consist primarily of newspaper clippings, but there are some event programs and correspondence included. The newspaper clippings document the performances of the Hillel Players, Hillel sponsored symposiums and lectures, as well as national and global concerns related to the Jewish community. The series also contains the B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation Log of 1940-41. Besides containing correspondence dealing with membership issues and announcing upcoming meetings and events, the Foundation Log also includes material from the Ann Arbor Jewish Committee's Refugee Student Campaign.
  - Hillel Scrap Book, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Hillel Players' Scrap Book, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Loose Material from Hillel Scrap Book, 1937 (Box 1)
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation Log, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Hillel Scrap Book, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Hillel Scrap Book, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Hillel Players' Scrap Book, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Hillel Players' Scrap Book, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
- Press/Publications
  Press/Publications series includes newspaper clippings, press releases, and newsletters. The newsletters in this series are published by the University of Michigan Hillel and have been arranged chronologically when dated, however, there are many gaps in the collection.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1936-1961 (Box 1)
  - News Releases, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Hillel Bulletin, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Friends Newsletter, 1990-1998 (Box 1)
  - UM Hillel Newsletter, 2000s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Bulletins and Publications, 1941, 1988 (Box 1)
- Events
  Events series reflects the diverse interests and activities of the University of Michigan Hillel. The series consists of calendar of events, announcements, flyers, programs, and posters. The past events documented in this series include lectures and performances by Allen Ginsberg, Elie Wiesel, Chris Rock, Dennis Miller and Oliver Stone. The series also contains programs and posters from the University of Michigan Hillel's Annual Conference on the Holocaust. The Conference on the Holocaust began in 1979 with the aim of educating the university community about the Holocaust through lectures, film, and artistic presentations representing a variety of perspectives.
  - Hillel Calendar of Events, 1984-2008, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Event Announcements and Flyers, 1940-1977 (Box 1)
  - Programs, general, 1942-1996 (Box 1)
  - Annual Conference on the Holocaust, Programs, 1984-2007, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Israel Conference Day, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Posters, general, 1980s-2000s (Box 3)
  - Posters, Annual Conference on the Holocaust, 1980s-2000s (Box 3)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library also has issues of Hillel News, Prospect, and Consider, a weekly non-partisan issues forum at University of Michigan. These materials are separately cataloged.